Let me show you a video.
>> Long-awaited guidance on single sex
spaces in Britain has confirmed that a
service such as a public [music] toilet
or a changing room must be used on the
basis of biological sex. This May, the
UK Equality and Human Rights Commission
published new guidance on how businesses
and other organizations can comply with
the Equality Act. It's supposed to be a
guide on how not to discriminate against
people. The code covers a whole bunch of
stuff, but basically all the
conversation has been about [music] what
many perceive as a new ban on trans
people using single sex spaces such as
toilets, changing rooms, and other
services. This has been a long time
coming. [music] In April 2025, the UK
Supreme Court passed a judgment which
ruled that sex for the purposes of
anti-discrimination law referred to sex
as recorded at birth. And yet, where
both [music] the ruling and the
subsequent guidance were meant to
provide clarity, only further confusion
has followed. I've come to a very hot
London to meet with Oscar Davies, a
human rights barrista, and also the UK's
first openly non-binary barristister,
too. I asked them what this guidance
actually says, what it means for trans
people, and how we got here. Everyone
watching this will probably have a
different level of knowledge about this
new EHRC uh guidance and the way that
it's been reported a lot in the uh news
lately is that there is sort of some new
rules, some new laws, it's been phrased
in all kinds of ways um pertaining to
single sex spaces and whether and how
trans people can or can't uh engage with
those, use those. Yeah. Um I guess like
the headline in a lot of cases has been
that this is effectively a ban on trans
people using those spaces. To what
extent is that like a fair
interpretation of what's happened here?
>> So Equality and Human Rights Commission
is what it's called. It's a quasi
independent body which operates
alongside
um governmental bodies. It's meant to be
essentially upholding human rights of
all people uh in particular minorities.
Now in the last few years um certain
members of the EHRC and heads etc uh
have had certain agendas which have
meant that basically what the EHRC puts
out or what it gets involved in and its
stance in it is not um in everyone's
view promoting human rights necessarily.
Sometimes it seems like it's doing the
opposite. And I think there's been some
serious inquiries
with international human rights groups
questioning whether the EHRC is fit for
practice given that it seems that
certain groups like trans people um are
not necessarily favored when they're
clearly a minority group who is you know
being attacked from all angles. Uh so
the equality and human rights commission
is basically meant to protect minority
groups. Whether it does so or not is
another question.
>> What is this guidance sort of intended
to do?
>> The guidance is meant to provide
practical examples that help um I
suppose service providers on one hand in
terms of understanding how to deal with
these issues but also helps judges make
fair and informed decisions um as to
whether something is discriminatory or
not basically. So it says near the start
of the guidance, this is intended for
courts and tribunals to um I think the
wording is take into account or consider
um so when they're making decisions and
so I think for service providers it can
be useful to take it into account as to
whether it's binding law is another
question and I think ultimately what
you're doing as a service provider
you're trying to provide a great service
obviously
and brackets, you're also trying to
avoid random claims from people.
Ultimately, we're in a position now
where unfortunately there can be
successful claims from two claimments
who are different and they both bring
claims about the same thing and they
could both be successful. So that's why
we're in a kind of legal quagmire at the
moment. when we're using the the phrase
service in terms of these what kinds of
things like a lot of the discussion has
been toilet like basically um what kinds
of things come under that umbrella of
services.
>> So services could be things like a cafe,
a bar, a club, a gym. Uh but it could
also be like a train station and it
could also be like a domestic violence
shelter. I mean, my kind of
[clears throat] I suppose hot take, if
that's a thing, is that these single sex
exemptions, which can be found in
schedule 3 of the Equality Act, were not
really designed for your average toilet
in, you know, some random bar like these
exemptions are really the exception to
the rule. So, to give you an idea of how
the framework works, it's like you have
Equality Act here. This basically says
uh you can't be discriminated against.
That's the basic level rule, ground
rules, right? So don't discriminate. You
then have what's called a carve out. So
the schedule 3 like exceptions are a
carve out and this says in some really
specific circumstances you can
discriminate. So say for example you're
uh providing a single sex service as a
domestic refuge shelter or something
says in some circumstances you could
allow that to be for women and not for
men and it could be legitimate if it's a
proportionate means of achieving a
legitimate aim blah blah blah. do the
proportionality exercise. So that is
kind the type of thing which in my view
schedule 3 was made for. I think it's a
misnomer and a misinterpretation of the
equality act in general to say that
every single toilet which says M and F
is a separate sex service or a se
separate sex space. I just don't think
that's what's been intended for the
Equality Act. Um and so there is this
kind of redeeming section in the EHRC
code for services uh which basically
says if someone is using a toilet which
is incidental to service brackets I
think all toilets are incidental to a
service but anyway um it's it won't be
appropriate to ask someone sex.
>> Mhm. And so I think there potentially is
some you know light in the guidance
which shows that actually these
exemptions are really specific and you
know legal tests and I just don't think
that you know the Paddington train
station toilets are for that kind of
rigorous legal assessment because it
says basically if you're going to use
one of these exemptions you have to have
done a proportionality exercise
>> balance everyone's rights um you know
potentially doing an equality impact
assessment have done all these things
and it's like realistically that's not
going to have happened. So when you're
considering your random cafe single
toilet and whether you have to make big
changes for that it's like I don't
really think that's what's being
envisaged when we're talking about these
schedule three exemptions. I just think
it's
society getting hypnotized by this
toilets issue or this changing room
issue where I'm like actually that's not
really what was envisaged in these
exemptions. I think it's interesting
what you're talking about there is this
kind of meeting point of the legal
aspect things and then this more kind of
like vibesy aspect of like most cafes
sort of have two toilets and there's
sort of probably a common sense approach
to how that works. Um we kind of this
latest guidance has been published um
that updates what you said the sort of
2011 guidance in the middle of that
there was this interim guidance which
was kind of as they were working on it I
guess from that 2011 guidance then what
has changed because I think
>> sort of weirdly this one of those things
that most people probably hadn't given a
huge amount of thought to like what is
the law surrounding a
>> a changing room toilet whatever kind of
service it is. um what what has changed
since the last set of guidance?
>> So, I'm glad you asked cuz I was going
to answer that anyway. Um, no. The 2011
guidance basically says, and this is
shown, if you look at it with all of
their examples, is basically saying, oh,
if you have um a separate sex space, so
like men's and women's, or if you have a
single sex space like women's domestic
refuge shelter, um, then basically this
is for people of that sex, but also
trans people who have changed their sex
or their gender, i.e. moved it over,
they're also allowed to be in that
service. So that's what it was saying
basically. So it's saying like a trans
woman can use a women's refuge. Um trans
man can use man's refuge. So that's
basically what it was saying and there
is examples of that. So I'm not even
like making it up. That's just what it
what the law was. So you had the 2011
which was trans-inclusive. You then had
the interim update from April uh last
year which said the ERC guidance
basically said um for a women's space
trans women can't go into it. I think
that's what the first or second bullet
point said but then there was a bullet
point at the end which said uh something
like and you should provide third spaces
when you can kind of thing. Um but yeah,
I mean arguably it wasn't super clear,
but basically that gave an impression to
service providers that they had to say
you have to go to the space of your
natal sex. And I mean imagine for a
moment like you're a trans man and
you've had all of the surgeries you can
think of like testosterone etc. You look
like a man. So trans man is like born
from a woman's body over to male. Um,
and then you're told all all of a sudden
that you have to actually use the
women's toilets and changing rooms and
you would be like, "Oh my god, like how
can I even do that?" So before there
wasn't this kind of obsessive focus on
what is your sex or what is your
perceived sex as opposed to you just
believe some that someone's in the right
toilet and the wrong toilet. And I think
it was quite interesting because there
was some there was uh questions to the
EHRC uh commissioner and uh saying you
know how can you possibly know how can
you know if someone's
Yeah. or or the other and she was like
oh it's a matter of common sense and
it's like but your common sense may be
different from someone else's.
>> Um and I actually think that it was a
more common sense approach before when
it's like oh some drunk guy goes into
women's but oh sorry I think you're in
the wrong toilet. If he is, he'll he'll
leave hopefully. If uh you know it's a
masculine presented woman, she'll like
no this is the right toilet, you know.
But like those things are quite rare.
>> Sorry for the embarrassment.
>> Yeah. Sorry for the awkwardness. Whereas
now it's like there's like heightened
scrutiny and um I think it's just leads
to more social policing, more
castigation of trans people, but also
anyone who's gender non-conforming. I
mean, even for me, like I don't really
wear makeup much these days or like do
any cool looks because it's kind of too
dangerous to be gender non-conforming
and going out in public. Like, I hate to
say it because, you know, obviously
people know me as like public figure
doing this work, which is great, but
like as a matter of like safety and
necessity, like I kind of have to go
undercover as like a gym bunny or like
whatever the thing is, you know? So, um,
yeah, I think there's heightened
scrutiny on having to ask people. And
there's even a whole section in the HRC
code which says, "Oh, what to do if you
want to ask someone and it basically
says like you should only ask someone
sex." Um, and this is a service
provider. It's not other service users.
So, like I don't think other service
users should be asking anyone anything
about this. Um, but in terms of service
providers, it says if you want to ask
them, be careful because you might
breach their privacy rights. You might
breach their article 8 rights. If you
really want to, then ask them. And uh
it's not appropriate to ask for evidence
because you never really know cuz a
gender recognition certificate can
change your sex anyway on a birth
certificate. So yeah, don't really ask
for evidence that you could like ask
them once maybe.
>> So this is the guidance, but also you
can't really do anything like
>> it's so strange. I mean, I suppose to
bring it down to that human level, what
is your interpretation for any trans
people that are watching, any non-binary
people, interex people that are watching
and going like, what does this mean for
how I live my daily life? because I know
you've talked one of the things you've
been really keen to specify is that it's
>> for service providers this guidance
>> and that's important for like two ways
because it's for
>> service providers rather than providers
of various other things.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's also service providers rather
than service users kind of what what
does that what what does that
distinction mean?
>> Um so to start with it should be
emphasized that this is a guidance for
service providers. is this is not the
guidance for employers that's coming
later and this is also not the guidance
for education providers that's these are
under separate parts of the equality act
so people kind of need to know that if
there's overlap then there's overlap but
ultimately this is service providers I
say service providers as opposed to
service users because the way that like
liability is attached is that an
individual say for example there's like
a cisgender woman who sees uh a
transgender woman in the changing room
and then gets really annoyed about it.
Who is the cisgender woman going to sue?
She's going to sue the gym. Let's say
it's a gym. Um, she's going to sue the
gym. And I don't know of a mechanism
where the individual service user can
sue the other individual service user
unless there's some sort of like
criminal liability like some sort of
physical assault or something. Um, so in
general terms, I see it as the service
user who wants to make a complaint can
complain to the service provider because
ultimately the service provider has
deeper pockets anyway. That's just how
these things work. And they say, "You're
not putting these guidance in place or
you're not doing this or that." The
service provider then has to make a
judgment call of saying, well, basically
when providing the service, is it
acceptable and have you done a
proportionality analysis to allow both a
sis woman and a trans woman into the
space? Um, if so, like who's it harming,
who's it not, and who's being reasonable
and who's not, that kind of thing. So,
yeah, for this reason, I suppose when
we're talking about if you're trans or
genderforming, I would say this guidance
is not necessarily for you. And I say
this in the sense of
um not wanting people to like do
unlawful things. Obviously, don't harass
anyone. Uh you know, don't assault
anyone. But at the same time, I think
there is a real danger with transgender
non-conforming people that they're kind
of consigned to the shadows. And this is
not just made up. I've got loads of DMs
or loads of people on their Instagram
being like, "Oh, now I'm too scared to
go out in public or like I haven't drunk
any water today so I don't have to pee."
You know, this kind of stuff. It's like
so sad, but it's is happening. And so,
I'd say, you know, just because this
EHRC guidance exists should not consign
you to the shadows.
>> Um, you should be able to live your life
publicly and fully and you make your own
decisions as to where you go basically.
Um, I don't think that, yeah, I I mean,
there's no sort of criminal liability
that's attached to going into this
toilet or that toilet, for example. So,
I can't advise you to like use whichever
toilet you want to, but at the same
time, it's like you deserve to be in
public. You deserve to be safe and you
deserve to go into spaces which are safe
for you. And so there's no actual legal
requirement on trans people to act a
certain way to use a particular
facility. It it's for the service
provider rather than a law for people
themselves.
>> Yeah. Exactly. And I think like the
worst thing that as long as you're not
doing like actual criminal damage or
something, the worst thing that can
happen to you is that uh you're
challenged by the service provider and
then they basically decide to kick you
out. But then that's pretty good grounds
for a gender reassignment discrimination
claim. So, you know, that's that's also
another risk that the service provider
probably doesn't want to deal with. So,
it's like there's basically it's it's
more about risk to service providers
rather than risk to service users. I
think a lot of trans people are
concerned, oh, is this going to change
my life? This and that. And it's like,
well, in theory, not really. like this
is merely a guidance for to be taken
into account by judges when they're
dealing with service type claims. Um
yes, okay, service providers are meant
to take it into account, but as a
service user, is it for you to be really
concerned about what this guidance is
saying or not? And I would argue not
really. you you sort of hinted there are
a couple of ways in which some of this
gets a little bit tangled I guess both
in the guidance but also the kind of
legal foundations for this
>> um one thing is around gender
recognition certificates and gender
recognition act um which
>> I think it's always worth saying came in
before the equality act so when the
equality act was being passed was
something lawmakers should should sort
of have known about and been taken into
account Um,
as things stand, trans people can get a
gender recognition certificate, which
through quite a lengthy and medicalized
process, um, means that you can
effectively
>> change your sex marker on various
different um, documents and previously
we understood it could um, act
accordingly.
>> Yeah.
>> A, how does this change that? And I
guess B, what does that mean for the
kind of function of a gender recognition
certificate?
>> Okay. So, should we go into the law?
Should we go into the law of this? Like
>> give you a shovel to start digging into
it.
>> No, I mean we Let's go into the law. So,
the law and then the law with an um
Okay. So, the law is this gender
recognition certificates arose because
of this case called Goodwin. This is
Christine Goodwin case. It went all the
way to Strasburg and this was like
around 2002 and basically it was like an
employment case and what arose from it
was that uh trans people in the UK
didn't have the gender recognition act.
So they had no no way of kind of like
proving that they were either a man or
woman because it was quite binary at
that time. In that judgment in the
European Court of Human Rights, it says
at paragraph 90, uh, this is not really
acceptable, England, UK, um, because
it's forcing trans people to be in an
intermediate zone, neither here nor
there. So they can't actually get access
to a load of their rights because
there's no means of recognition.
>> Um, so that then led to a declaration of
incompatibility and that's what led to
the Gender Recognition Act being made in
2004. Gender recognition act. Basically,
if you apply for gender recognition
certificate, as you said, there's loads
of things like you need to be 18, have
two letters from various doctors, uh you
know, intend to live in your acquired
gender for your whole life, have have
had lived in your acquired gender for 2
years, etc. But the point of that is
that it changes both your sex and your
gender, meaning that on your birth
certificate, you can apply for it to be
in your acquired one. Although arguably
a trans person would say, well, I've
been in that gender my whole life.
Internally,
>> um, so that was the whole point of a
GRC. Now, GLC's, as you've said, are
quite difficult to get. Um, and this is
useful for things like marriage and
yeah, being in various spaces. The
problem now we have is that the Supreme
Court said, well, sex under the Equality
Act uh, means biological sex. And so
therefore, when you have a GRC with like
what's the point of a GRC? It has
certain functions. And this means that
under laws outside of the Equality Act,
your sex could say you're a trans woman,
your sex could be F female, but within
the Equality Act, you're still male.
So what has the UK done by accident? Put
trans people into an intermediate zone
which is not compliant with Goodwin
which is the whole point of the Gender
Recognition Act 2004. So we're in this
strange position where trans people are
treated as neither here nor there
putting non-binary and insects to aside
for a moment that focusing on binary
trans people. Um which I don't think is
compliant with our convention rules.
We're still signary to the European
Convention on Human Rights. So that's a
big mess. And uh I think that now to
answer your question in a long type of
way, GRC's are barely worth the paper
they're written on because the function
is kind of meaningless. It's meant to
change your sex as a matter of
recognition by the state. And now as per
Supreme Court judges, they say actually
no, under the Equality Act, i.e. all of
your discrimination rights, you're
actually a man. You're a trans woman.
And so you can see how that can be
incred in incredibly denigrating for any
trans person for the judiciary and to
some extent the state not to recognize
it. Now we could get out of this whole
mess if the parliamentarians and
politicians were brave enough to just
say, "Okay, let's amend Equality Act.
Let's say sex here also means
certificated sex. End of." Or if they
opened it up and said, "Uh, yes, okay,
non-binary intersects can go in here.
It's definitely protected." But they're
not doing that. And so what is annoying
is that we're having to bash it out in
the courts which have horrible delays
because of lack of funding for
judiciary. Um and yeah, we're in this
awful position where trans people are
now treated as like a kind of tertiary
class of people, which I just think is
so shameful. It's like when people um
when people attack trans people, I'm
like, how could you attack these people
who have such few rights are already
vilified by the media and you're
attacking them for merely going to the
toilet? Do you not have something better
to do? M I mean I mean one thing in in
terms of the kind of backstory of this I
guess which um
>> I guess when we think about the law
changing usually most of us think about
an MP writes a bill sort of drops down
to parliament introduces it it you know
it gets passed and the law changes that
way and the main way that the law seems
to have changed around this has been
through the courts and um particularly
with antitrans campaigners
>> pushing through a number of different
court cases to try and get the law
changed in various different ways. Um
why do you think that has been the way
that this has happened rather than them
I don't know setting up a petition or uh
writing to their MP?
>> It's an interesting question. I think
yeah what we call lawfare is something
which over the last 10 20 years has
really become such a focal point. Um, I
think that the organizations that who
are anti-trans are very highly organized
and highly funded by certain evangelical
organizations in the states, for
example. Um, and yeah, they so they've
chosen the vehicle of litigation. Why
they've chosen it, I don't know exactly.
I don't really speak to them, you know,
one-on-one, as you can imagine. They
usually don't like me. um sad times. But
no, I mean I think it's an interesting
question and it raises
certain really difficult questions about
potential biases uh amongst the
judiciary. Do they do they think that
the judiciary is an easier target to get
through um
bigotry disguised as uh protecting other
rights and it seems that they've been
quite successful. A lot of those
campaigners will say that they are sort
of frame themselves as feminist groups
will say that they are doing this
because they see competing rights
between trans people particularly trans
women and uh cis women and that they are
sort of doing this in the name of
feminism and in the name of women's
rights. To what extent do you think this
guidance does um make sis women's lives
easier or better or does it not?
>> I think the EHRC guidance on services
makes all women's lives worse. It puts a
sharp focus on women's bodies which is
similar to what the four women Scotland
case did. I don't think it's helping
really any feminist objectives to put a
sharp focus on what a woman is. You
know, this like billion dollar question
which everyone is obsessed with. And
it's like should you be asking what a
woman is as opposed to how can we get
everyone equal rights? Um, and I think
that it's in my view completely
unfeminist to have to force women to
justify uh their bodies and themselves
in alleged attempts for equality.
Whereas for me it's like if you're
forcing women and trans women to justify
their existence of just their being
that's just going back to biological
essentialism which is completely
antithetical to any movement towards
equality for all. So I always think it's
such a misnomer to say oh this is to
help the feminist courts and it's like
but who are you helping here? you know,
masculine women are going to be
challenged more now because of this
guidance, because of these cases. Uh, is
that helping them? Is it helping them to
be harassed? Potentially, but I don't
see how it's helping them to get equal
rights. And yes, I understand the
anxiety of like, you know, women's
rights have been fought for so hard,
80s, '90s, second wave feminism, etc.
But and and I understand the anxiety of
men trying to encroach on that. But
there needs to be a true understanding
that like trans women are not the same
as men. Trans women are read uh often as
women or as a version of women and they
receive both misogyny and trans
misogyny. So there's often often a kind
of like double ex exclusion. Um, and I
don't see, you know, it's also like I
think there's a certain anxiety about
non-binary people, for example. You
know, I'm not trying to get into a
woman's space. I'm not I'm not an idiot.
Like, I understand objects matter. And
also, it's not to say that saying a
trans woman can go into a woman's space
is saying that any trans person can go
into that space. I actually noticed that
this was an anxiety because someone
commented on one of my things the other
day. They were like, "No, I agree that
trans women can go to women's faces, but
the problem is now you've just said that
trans can be everything like gender
fluid and and this and that." And I'm
like, "No, no, that's not how it works.
It's like trans, trans plus as a broad
umbrella is here. You've then got like
trans women, trans men, then got all the
other ones like gender fluid,
non-binary, agender, blah blah blah."
And it's like if it's a women's space,
they're trying to say trans women can go
in, not all of these other people. Um,
so I think there can be quite a lot of
misunderstanding of what these terms
mean. And again, it kind of goes back to
language. And to some extent, I, you
know, I kind of hate identity politics.
I hate like discourse in general. Like
it's so exhausting. It's like why can't
people just be and just don't be like a
horrible person? Um,
>> there are some there are some
organizations that I think uh from my
understanding sort of feel like they
were taking quite a common sense
approach. there was a common sense
approach and was an inclusive one that
have now felt like they have to against
their own wishes make very different
decisions. I think the highest profile
ones probably being the women's
institute the WI and girl guiding both
of whom put out
>> quite like difficult to read statements
almost of of being like we now have to
exclude trans people. We didn't want to
do this but that is what the law is now.
what kind of risk would they be placing
themselves at had they um decided to
fight it I guess.
>> Yeah. So with those ones um girl girl
guides and women's
>> institute yeah I think the I mean the
responses were really disappointing for
many people not just trans people also
you know I had messages from sis women
being like I've been a member of this
for 30 years and I can't believe this
stance. Um I think that those responses
were potentially made too quickly and uh
also assuming that the Supreme Court
says certain things when it doesn't. You
know the Supreme Court doesn't require
exclusion that if you read Foreign
Scotland and you point me to that
paragraph then so be it. But like it
doesn't require exclusion of of
organizations.
Um, I think even with this guidance now,
there's potential ways that you can
still be inclusive even if you're
provide even if you're providing a
single sex or or a service generally
speaking for for women or for men, there
are still ways that you can do it um,
and be trans-incclusive.
And there's various paragraphs which I
can advise you on if you come to me,
which I can't remember right now,
basically. Um but yeah so I think if
they hadn't done that then they would
face more litigation risks from gender
critical people but now that they have
done that they face more risks from
trans or trans allies who can also bring
a associative discrimination claim based
on the fact that they're associated to
like say a mom has a trans kid can't go
to girl guides could she could bring a
gender reassignment uh associated
discrimination claim as well as the
child who could bring one. So yeah,
basically there's there's no way that
you can avoid possible protection uh
possible claims. But I think the thing
which is a real shame is that through
certain threatening tactics of certain
organizations
um there's been
certain ways of describing the for women
Scotland case and the guidance which is
not accurate and overextends the
exclusion uh about of trans people and
certain organizations have basically
collapsed to that pressure. Um, so yeah,
having said that, I think for for both
of those, there's been offers on the
other side saying, you know, if you
actually want to be trans-inclusive
again, we will protect you and fund it.
So, I think those offers have not yet
been taken, and maybe they should.
>> So, I wanted to end by asking about some
of the kind of resistance to this, I
guess, or or efforts to try and and
change this. Um the most immediate I
guess is that this guidance has been uh
and I'm aware this is more parliamentary
stuff so it's slightly out of your
wheelhouse but has been laid before
parliament where it will sit for 40 days
which we're now a bit through um and
that it comes into power um unless MPs
actively oppose it.
>> Yeah,
>> there is a motion to try and disprove it
within parliament. Are you able to talk
about that at all? I think at the moment
there's been attempts to have a debate
about it. Um but the debate has not been
taken up which means that it will stay
as it's laid. It's only if the debate is
actually taken up that it can be
challenged and put back to the HRC. Um
so it's not looking likely that it will
change but it could. And so if people
would like that to debate to happen and
we do get this out in time, they can uh
write to their MPs and try and get them
to
>> they can write to their MPs and say,
"Look, I'm not happy with this. This is
impossible for service providers to
enforce and is awful trans people,
general conforming people, mascul etc.
They can write to MP and ask them to
take a stand, in which case the MP will
sign up onto the thing." I think there's
like 120 MPs at the moment. Um, and so
yeah, that might make a difference. I
believe there's also efforts to try and
um appeal some of the more foundational
kind of legal aspects of this. Uh one of
which I believe you're involved in a
case that's going to the EHRC.
>> Oh yeah. So that's the Dr. Victoria
Mloud versus UK case. Um this is a case
about Dr. Victoria Mloud and others
tried to intervene at the Supreme Court
before the decision was made about the
forum in Scotland and their intervention
was rejected which meant that basically
almost all of the organizations being
heard by the Supreme Court were
anti-trans in some sort of way. Um which
meant that the Supreme Court's decision
was taken on an unfair unfair balance.
So we run this argument to Strasburg and
we put in the application um on the
basis of article 6 which is right to a
fair trial I.e. Dr. Victoria Cloud did
not have uh access to a right to a fair
trial if she was not allowed to
intervene and therefore also there's an
infringement on her article 8 rights
because she's had a GRC for like 20
years um and now she can't have access
to loads of the things that she used to.
Mhm.
>> So that's kind of the that case
>> as someone who kind of lives and
breathes this
>> night and day. Um hopefully you don't
breathe it at night. Hopefully you get
some some rest. But as someone who lives
and read this day by day, if you were
sort of given the scope to try and
design a version of this guidance that
was
inclusive,
um that didn't discriminate against
trans people
and was therefore more workable like
what what would your starting point be
for that?
I suppose in a in an ideal scenario, we
would have guidance which
which believes trans people as to who
they say they are. So, it allows trans
women to go to women's spaces with the
restrictions that are still, you know,
you have to be able to justify it. It
allows trans men to go to men's spaces.
I would also like there to be more
recognition of non-binary and interex
people. Uh which sometimes means you may
need legislation for that. So for
example, the legislators could open up
the Equality Act and add in interex as a
protected characteristic. They could add
in non-binary as a protected
characteristic. The problem at the
moment is that if non-binary and interex
are not recognized as a matter of
recognition, they don't have access to
their full legal personhood. And
therefore in my article which will come
out soon, it doesn't allow them to have
access to the article 8 rights. And so
we need that kind of recognition of
them. I think within the code there's
some recognition of non-binary and
gender fluid people, which is good. It
says they may be covered under section
7, which is gender assignment. So you
can maybe bring a claim. Um, but
ultimately a a good services code would
be inclusive of trans people, allow
trans people to use the spaces that they
want to use, would still give examples
of when something is or isn't uh
acceptable because that's what the
services code is for, but it wouldn't
use prejudice and it wouldn't use
exclusion as a starting point. Um, and
it would be more similar to the 2011
code. I think the 2011 code is really
good actually in that it seems very well
balanced and there was this whole
discourse about whether uh the equality
act was meant to have biological added
in and I think one of I can't remember
her name but she was one of the uh
parliamentarians at the time who
>> Harry Harmon um no not Harry Harmon it
was another lady anyway whose name
escapes me but she said the whole
purpose of uh equality act was that sex
was meant to be inclusive of trans
people. There's this other case law
called P and S which is European Court
of Justice which says when you reassign
someone's sex sorry when you reassign
someone's gender you also reassign their
sex. So this whole thing about um
biological sex is also a misnomer and I
think is completely crazy that we have
to be hypnotized by it. And it's like
actually why don't we work on making
spaces more inclusive as opposed to more
exclusionary
um and kind of try and get society
society to be better. I think there's a
big difference between what someone
thinks in their head and what they
should be able to say out loud in
public, whether it's at your local gym
or whether it's in the workplace. And I
think people more and more are trying to
have full license to say whatever you
want. But I'm sorry, you can think
whatever you want internally, but as
soon as it becomes external, you are
subject to certain restrictions, which
may be by law, but they may also be by
social politeness, for example. And if
you're really trying to be a horrible
person in a public space, I would look
in the mirror, and if you're pointing at
someone, there's always three fingers
pointing back. So maybe look at yourself
before you start coming for other
people. Thank you so much for watching
this video. something a little bit more
timely than we often are able to make on
this channel. Uh, and that's something
that we're working particularly a bunch
on at the moment. Uh, with my new show,
Slow Newsuesday, which you can watch two
episodes of a week here on YouTube if
you head over to the relevant channel,
which you can watch four episodes of
every single week over on Nebula. If
you've watched a bunch of my videos
before, you will have heard of Nebula.
is a premium streaming service made by
myself and a bunch of other inquisitive
creators. Some of those news-based, some
of those educationbased, some of those
uh deep thinkers about uh culture and
the world around us, as well as allowing
you to watch all of my videos and their
videos ad and sponsor free. It also is
home to an ever growing catalog of
exclusive films [music] and shows, too.
That list of films and shows includes
Slow Newsuesday. It also includes my
debut feature film, Boomers. If you want
to watch something a little bit more
positive about the trans experience, it
also includes Jesse Gender's fantastic
short film, Identities, which came out a
couple of years ago now, but is a
fantastic [music] exploration of uh
gender identity through a kind of sci-fi
lens. Really, really worth a watch. If
you want to sign up to watch all of that
fantastic exclusive content, then you
can do so using my link,
go.bul.tv/tomlas.
TV/tomicholas.
That gets you 50% off an annual plan,
bringing your total uh subscription
amount down to just £250 per month or
whatever the equivalent is where you
are. Signing up to Nebula using that
link go.nebula.tv/tonicholas
also uh helps us support the channel a
whole bunch. You get a little kickback
when you sign up. You also get paid more
when you watch our stuff over on Nebula
rather than on YouTube. Uh it really
does help to support us in a whole bunch
of ways. Thank you so much for watching
this video and supporting all that we're
trying to do. Uh that link again is
go.nebula.tv/tomicholas.
Thanks so much once again and I will see
you over on Nebula. All that's left me
to do is to say a massive thank you to
the people uh who support my work by
being signed up to the top tier over on
my Patreon page at
patreon.com/tomicholas.
Those people are Richard, Gary, Dick on
Spain, Bill Mitchell, ZC Reese, Zoe
Alden, Alexander Blank, Neil Zildgard,
Sophia R, Sergio Suarez, Richard Rapun,
Gabriel Ko, Jimmy Dunn, Fiasco Linguini,
Agent Maxwell, Glenn Sugdan, Emil
Jarabar, Yillimson, Paulus Edus, Sam
Portonatu, and not Medi. if you want to
join them in getting access to uh often
early access to stuff we're working on,
little updates what we're working on
through my weekly blog, the Friday
Update, and a bunch of other stuff, as
well as just supporting uh our work
here, then you can find out how to do so
at patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again and I'll see you in the next